Such as what is condition variable
How to design a system that can handle five hundred million users
Questions like this are not only critical for job interviews
But also very important for daily work in this video
I will tell you five stories that can help you to master multi threading programming
This story helped me tremendously before
So nowadays if you give me any reading questions within five seconds
I will get it and find a solution for it
It is that powerful
Because these stories actually tell five design patterns that are critical for multi threading programming
In this video
I will not only explain what these five patterns are
But also share the source code to you
So that you don't have to start from scratch
So these five design patterns they built upon each other
They start from the very basic
But in the end they will cover the most sophisticated scenarios
So this with long time and dive into our stories
So the first story is called
Explaining what issues you can have in multi threading programming
And also introduce a design pattern called safe and smart lock
Which will help you to resolve those issues
See you have a blackboard
And you have two gentlemen
Danny and peter
Both gentlemen want to write their name on the blackboard
Danny wants to write my name is danny
And peter wants to write my name is peter
The problem is these two gentlemen don't cooperate each other
So when danny is writing my name
And before he can continue and peter's jumping
And right
My name is peter again
And then danny has a chance to finish his words
So in the end
Because these two gentlemen don't cooperate with each other
The blackboard will end up with something like this
My name is my name is danny
Peter
This kind of lack of collaboration between two people
Is precisely what happened in a multi threading environment
The blackboard in programming terms we call it shared resource
Because it is shared by both danny and peter and danny and peter
They represent two threads
Tennis to it and peter read
And the fact that they both simultaneously try to write down their name
And double rubbish output
We call this this condition
Let's use the code to illustrate this
So we created a c plus plus file called thread samples dot cpp
Within which we include all the necessary headers
Thread and i will stream that we will use cue
So we include this upfront
And of course it claims the m space std
The first thing we need to do is to write a function called then right
So this function takes one parameter blackboard
Which is a string reference
If you don't know what the reference is basically in
C plus plus a reference allows you to modify blackboard which is defined outside of tennis
Right and what this function does is
Try to add my name is danny into the blackboard
So
But between each words we will insert a sleep function to force
That is right to sleep from one to three million seconds to slow down the writing process
Because we want later on
Peter has a chance to jump in before danny finishes writing
If danny runs too fast
Peter might not have the chance to jump in before danny finishes is writing
And then we cannot demonstrate the issue
We define a peter's right exactly the same
Except that it was my name is peter instead of dining
So these are the two functions
And then we will define a test function
We call demo resource conflict within this function
We will of course define our blackboard which is a string
And then we will create our first thread
We call it dis thread and passing in any function
And the parameter blackboard into this thread
For those who don't know how to create a thread in c plus
Plus here's a quick explanation
So here then is thread is a thread object
It takes two parameters
The first one it is a function name
Which is that is right we defined here
And the second one is the parameter for the that is right function
So because here it accepts blackboard
So here we pass the blackboard which we defined here as a second parameter
And we put this into a reference rapper for those who don't know what reference
Rapper is you can google it
Basically this ref wrapper allows you to pass the blackboard object as a reference
That's all you need to know after we create that thread
It will immediately be executed in computer
So bear that in mind
And next we will create a second thread
We call peter read
Which do exactly the same thing
But to call peter right
And then we will wait the then read to finish
And we will wait the peter read to finish
How we wait
We call the drawing function
And after both threats finished
We will output what the two threats wrote on the blackboard
So we will put this stuff to see out and let's see what happened
And of course we need to put this function there
More resource conflict into our main function
So that we can sees this result
So now we finish the code
Let's compile it and to see these results
So it compile and let's run it
And to see what happened you see here
The output is my my name name is is danny peter
So it's rubbish
And the reason let's explain that again is because
When these two threads run simultaneously
Both sides were trying to write to the blackboard string
Because they did not collaborate
So when danny write function was trying to write its string
And before it can finish peter right
So it jumps in
That is what you see how to resolve this problem
It's very easy see in the danny peter's story
Both gentlemen had their own pen so that they can write
Whenever they want in next story
We will give these two gentlemen only one pen
So whoever can get the first has his right to write down his name
After he finishes
He will have to turn that pen
And the next gentleman will get that pen and his words
The key here is that we will have only one pen for two gentlemen
And at any given point of time
Only one gentleman can have the pen and can finish work
The second critical point is that after the gentleman finished his work
He must return that plan
Otherwise the second gentleman will wait forever to get a pen
So that's also very important
So let's use code to demonstrate this
So here we write a new function called peter right with mutex
And this function take an extra parameter
We call it mutex
This mutex is a pen in our story
At any point of time
Only one gentleman
Either danny or peter will get a pen
In our case we get the mule text
But how exactly does peter to get same pen
In this case mutex
This actually is called mutex lock function
The lock means it gets a pen
And then we call the previous function peter wright
So that peter can write its name on the blackboard without interruption
Because gets a pen
Then it does have the pen
But after peter finished its work
It's very important for peter to turn the pen
How does it return the pen
Unlock it
Unlock the mutex
So this is the new function peter right with mute
And we need the standard version of the new function
Everything is the same
Then the lol text then is right
And then danny returned and unlocks the new text
So here's a test code as usual
We define the blackboard
And then we define the new variable mutex
This is our pen very important
And then we pass a new function
Danny is right with mutex to the danny thread
And also we pass a new parameter mutex
So we do the same thing for peter thread
And then we let them do the work
We wait for both threats to finish
And then we print out what it's on the blackboard
Of course we need to puts a test function into our main function
So let's run the code and to see what happens
So we compile it
And we run the code
So now everything works properly
My name is danny and my name is peter beautiful
However this version of the code has at least three potential problems
So the first issue what
If any of these two gentlemen forget to turn the pen
In our case to unlock the mute
After they get a after the loxy mutex
There are several scenarios that this can happen
The programmer just forget to call the unlock function
And there's an accepting happened during the
Let's see when peter called mutex locks
And when the thread is trying to write stuff on blackboard and boom
For some reason there's an exception and so the threat dies
And there's no for this thread to call unlock function
And in this case
That thread will wait because the mutex will be locked forever
Fortunately c plus pass provide a unique solution to solve this issue
In its standard library
It provides a class called unique log
Which will guarantee that you unlock the mutex
How does it do it
Because c plus plus has a unique feature called structure
This will be guaranteed to call when an object gets destroyed
Either because of an exception
Or because it just finished it works and goes out of scope either way
If you put the unlock function into the destructor
It will be guaranteed to call
So what this means is that using unique log
You only need to lock the musics
And you never need to unlock the music
Because the system will automatically unlock it
No matter what happened
Even if you encounter an exception
So this unique lock is the first part of our design pattern
It's a smart lock
Because it can automatically unlock it
That's why we call it smart lock
So let's look at the code how we implement this
So here instead of we write directly a mutex log function
We actually will delete that
And we will replace it with this line of code here we just created a log object
Which will lock the mutex automatically
Because it's a smart lock
We don't need to unlock it
So let's delete this unlock function
So this is how we use a smart lock
We lock it
And we let the peter to do its work
And after peter finishes work
The function will finish and will go out of scope
So automatically
The mutex will be unlocked and even better so
Even if we are executing the peter right function
And there's an exception happened
The lock will guarantee the music be unlocked
Isn't that beautiful
So let's do the same thing to the dennis right mutex function now
Let's compile the code and see what happened
Compile it and on see it works as before
Just as if we unlock the new text directly
So now we understand the first part of the patent
The smart lock
And we resolve the issue that if somebody either forget to unlock the mutex
Or an accepting happened
And we never get the chance to release a lock
We got this covered
But we still need to cover the last issue
Which is what if somebody forget to lock the mutex in the first place
And then they access the resource directly in our story
What if peter doesn't respect the rule
Instead of using the pen shared by danny
He actually pulled up his own pen
And while danny is writing on the blackboard
He is using his pen writing his name on the blackboard
He completely bypassed the pen mechanism
And this could happen either because of a junior developer
Who is not familiar with this lock and unlock mechanism
Or because your team is developing a very complex system
And somebody somewhere forgot to lock the mutex and access the resource directly
Even in our case
What if that's somebody instead of calling the peter
Wright
W's ill text
It just make a human mistake
Instead of let the peter's thread calling the right function
Peter wright with mutex
We mistakenly called the peter wright function
Which doesn't have the mutex protection
And if you put these two lines of code together
All those arrows will come back
And how do we resolve this issue
This is the second part
The safe part of the design pattern
The concept of this solution is very simple
Instead of allowing danny and peter to write directly on the blackboard
We actually put the blackboard into a safe
So that either danny or peter cannot write on the blackboard
Unless they got a proper lock to unlock the safe
That's it before they can right onto the blackboard
So they have to use a lock to unlock the safe
So that they can get the access to the blackboard
So this part of the pattern
We call it the safe part of the pattern resolves the issue
What if a developer forget to lock the mutex
So let's take a look at how we implement this solution
So the implementation of this concept of safe in this design pattern is a class
We called mutesafe
It's a template class
It's actually a combination of two key components
Mutex and the resource it tries to protect
That's why it has two private data members
The mutex itself and the resource pointer it tries to protect
So for the resource you have to pass
This was pointer in the constructor
And delete the resource when the mutex safe is destroyed
This means that the mutex save object on this resource
It tries to protect which we will show it in our code later
And because the mutex safe class is a mutex
That's why it implements all three key apis of mutex lock
Unlock and try lock
So that it behave exactly the same as a mutex object
And the key of this class is a function acquired
It does nothing more than just returns a resource
It accepts a parameter unique log object
This means that this function forces you to pass it a log object
This guarantees that you cannot access these resources before your lock is safe
Okay
So now we understand how music safe works
Let's use it to protect our blackboard
So because a blackboard is a string
This type defines a music safe string as a string new type
And then we write a new function to allow danny to write his name
Is safely on the blackboard using our safe mechanism
So we write a function as safe that is right
Which takes a parameter as a safe instead of stream
So within this function we will create a log
But this time instead of a log
A mutex with log the safe itself
And then we acquire the blackboard from the safe by passing the log
We just created to the acquire function
So since we get the blackboard
We call the dis right function
As we just did before
And then we return and we do this to the peter wright
And after we finish this two function
Let's write a test function to show how we actually use it
So the function name is called test safe
Smart lock within this function
Of course we create a safe
And when we create the safe
We knew a string as our blackboard
Remember what we said
A safe will own the resource is tries to protect
So in this case save owns the blackboard
This string we just created
And now let's create the danny read
This time we pass a newly created function
Save that right instead of the old function
And then we pass the safe instead of the blackboard into this thread
We do the same to the peter thread
And then let's wait them to finish
And then let's try to print out the blackboard
But remember because we put the blackboard into the safe
If we cannot access blackboard directly anywhere
So this time we have to lock the safe again
And then we acquire the blackboard in our main street
And then we print it out
And then of course we put this test function into our main function
It looks very similar
Let's compile the code
And let's all the code and everything runs smoothly
So now let's compare this traditional mutex lock and unlock code
With our safe code to say
What's the difference
Let's put it side by side
So if you compare this two version of code
The will take safe version and the normal lock version
The only two things you need to change
Number one when you lock the lock is safe
Instead of the mutex directly and number two before you can access the protected resource
You have to acquire it and pass the log you just created to the acquire function
This guarantees that you cannot forget lock this resource
That's it
No other changes
But it helps you to avoid the humor arrows
That is very difficult to debug later on
Okay
Now we understand the safe and smart lock design pattern
Next move to the next story
Where danny needs to keep watching the stock price changes
Because he wants to sell his stock at ninety dollars
However nobody knows when the stock price will change
So then it has to keep watching the stock change all the time
This leaves him no time to do his other work
By the end of the story
You will find that danny finds a very good solution to solve this problem
You can watch your next story here or down below
This channel is all about digital transformation and technology
If you are interested in these topics
Please join our community down below
Where you can discuss these topics with other people with the same interest